<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A breife recantacion of maystres Missa and howe she accuseth the slouthfulnesse of her chapleyns, with her lamentable departyng vnto her father the Pope. 1.5 4.8.</title>
            <author>I. M., fl. 1548.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1548</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06681</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17137</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106358</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842076</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842076</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6700</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06681)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6700)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 604:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A breife recantacion of maystres Missa and howe she accuseth the slouthfulnesse of her chapleyns, with her lamentable departyng vnto her father the Pope. 1.5 4.8.</title>
                  <author>I. M., fl. 1548.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>R. Wyer?],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1548]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The recantacion of maystres missa.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A(-A7-8).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6700:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6700:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6700:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6700:2"/>
            <p>¶ A breife recan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacion of mayſtres Miſſa, And howe ſhe accuſeth the flouthfuineſſe of her Chapleyns, with her lamentable departyng vnto her Father the Pope. 1.5 4.8.</p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>¶ Euery tre that my heauenly Father hath not planted ſhall be plucked vp by the rotes.</q>
               <bibl> Mathew the.xv.</bibl>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
         <div type="preface_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:6700:3"/>
            <head>¶ The preface to the reader.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>A.S.I.M.S.D.F.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>BE thou not moued gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryll Reader bycauſe that I haue not obſerued y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> due order of a Recanta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion, for it is not onely a recantacion, but alſo an accuſacion or complaynte of the flouthfulnes of her Chaplaynes that haue ſo longe tyme orſceyued her, and borne her in hande that ſhe had al her powre of the ſcripture, and now in tyme of nede neuer one of them will ſtande to the proufe of it, but lette it paſſe as though they hat neuer ben co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentynge to the ſame as thou mayſte more playnly perce yue in readynge the booke.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Fare well the.i. of Iune.</salute>
               <signed>By me. <hi>I. M.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:6700:3"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>E it knowen vnto all men, that I maiſtres Miſſa a woman of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table fame, haueregned aboue.iii.C.yeares. And haue ben eſtemed all that tyme as a goddes, whiche coulde delyuer ſoules from hell and purgatorye. The which beynge now truely tryed and duely ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued by the ſcripture to be contrarye, I am conſtrayned and alſo inforſed, to reſorte hyther at this preſent tyme for to Becanté, reuoke, &amp; vtterly to denye all the foreſayd powre and authoryte. To thentente that the people maye leaue all ſuche vayne hope, and blynde truſle as they haue hadde in me. It is not vnknowne gentyll audyence that it hath ben thought, yea and faythful<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly beleaued that I deſcended from chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſte and his diſcyples, and is thought ſo ſtyll vnto many. But I ſhall (god wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge) or I make an ende, ſo opyn the matter, that they ſhall know from
<pb facs="tcp:6700:4"/>Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s I came &amp; for what cauſe I was created. And bycauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> my chapleyns wolde nedes haue me to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſupper of the lorde, and nowe wyll not ſtande to the proufe of it. I ſhall alſo ſhew howe farre I dyffer from the true ſupper of the lorde and wyll playnely proue that I haue none affynite at all therwith. Notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng, I haue both taught and faythfully beleued the ſame myſel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fe by the falſe parſwaſion of my crafty chaleyns, whiche continually kept me blynde with Hoc eſt enim corpus meum. And for the more ſuraunce anorned and decked me with parthes and p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>es of the Goſpell and Hyſtell, Wherwith they myght alſo blynd the people, inſo moche that I thought my ſelfe chack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate with god almyghty, and euen as good as the ſecond parſon in trinate. Whiche falſe and hlynd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> exrour I vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly forſake and deny here before you all. Cornfeſſyug that I haue none ſuch power nor aurthoryte neyther from
<pb facs="tcp:6700:4"/>God nor his diſciples. Nor had no be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynyuge of them. For truly I had my begyunyng of my father the pope who the begate me of dame Auaritia. And I had alſo many goodlye Chyldren by hym and his cardinalles, as miſſa y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uneris, miſſa propluuia, maſſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomine Ieſu, miſſa deſancta trimtate and alſo one called maſſe of Scala celt whiche was of more powre and vertue then all the reſt, for as my Chapleyns ſayd ſhe wolde not ſtycke to Scale the walles of heuen, that they were not ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kyn inquirlye whom ſhe brought, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was there any condempned in to hell y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhe coulde not fetche out of theyr frendes were able to purchaſe her, the which I canfeſſe is but a tanteſye and dreme of theyr owne inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For yfa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny ſuche powre had ben graunted bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to me or to my doughter, then had the bloud of Chriſt ben ſhed in vayne. And moreouer they wolde make Chriſte a very fuit to come downe from the heye
<pb facs="tcp:6700:5"/>throne of god his father, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r to be whyp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ped ſcourged, yea and ſuffer moſte: uell death, to ſaue mannes ſoule from hell: and yf it myght be bought for a lytell money. But truely neyther I, nor my doughters, haue any ſuch poure to fetch any ſoule from hell. Yea I feare me ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther leſt we haue ſent the uſandes thy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. But yf we haue, they belyke to be there a good whyle or euer we fetche them out. Nether dyd my father beget me for any ſuche purpoſe, for this cauſe onelye was I created that by me they myght maynteyne theyr honoure. And that by the meanes of me they myghte increaſe theyr ryches, and fyiltheyr co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers, and by me ſyr Ihon<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lacklatyne that coulde do nothynge but mumble vp matens, ſynge a maſſe was had in aſmoche reputacion as a ryght honeſt and wellerned man. And heare I do co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſe that I haue ben a very pyckpurſe yea and worſe then a pickpurſe, for I haue ben euen a ſtronge thefe and a
<pb facs="tcp:6700:5"/>robber of all nacions. I ſpared nether kynge ne prynce tyche ne poore, but I and my doughters, with my brother dirige wolde haue a ſayeng with them and in this poynte onely I folowed the Scripture, in that I had no reſpect of parſons ſo that they broughte money, but yf they broughte none they were lyke to go vniuſtyfyed home, For the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4+ letters">
                  <desc>••••…</desc>
               </gap>che thyng I repente me nowe. But (as I haue promyſed) I wyll <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>owe in fewe wordes declare how far I oyffer from the true ſupper of the Lorde in ſo moch that you ſhal well perceyue that I haue none affinite therwith we rede in the ſcrypture. Luke xxij. That chriſt the nyghte he was betrayed as he ſat at ſupper with the .xij. Toke bread and gaue thankes gaue it to his eiſcypies ſayinge, take, eate, this is my body whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che is gyuen for you, but we do not rede in all the ſcripture that euer he or any of his diſciples put on any ſuch maſking geare and went vp to an alter and lyf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:6700:6"/>it ouer his heade. It foloweth in the text after they had ſupped lykwyſe he toke the cup and gaue thankes and gaue it to his diſciples, ſayinge drynke et this all you, this is the cuppe of the newe Teſtamente in my bloude which ſhall be ſhet for you, but were not t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e that be dronke of all, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> them with the empty cup Marke well rowe gentle au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ence I own this gears doth a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e. Chriſt gaven to his diſciples as he ſat at ſupper with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but my chap <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ey<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s gette them a good wave of to an a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ter, and eate it vp alone Chriſte toke the cup and gaue it to his diſciples, but my thapleyns wyll let no body touche the cup, but them ſelues. Neyther wyll they gyue any man drynke with them. Chriſte gaue it at ſupper, but my chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leyus take it to theyr breakfaſt. Thus maye you ſe good audience y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chriſtes inſtitution and theyr ordynaunce, do not onely diſagre, but alſo the one doth playnlye repoungne ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> the other,
<pb facs="tcp:6700:6"/>nether can it be any other wyſe, ſeyng that the one came of god, &amp; the other but of man. Wherfore the one muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des haue anende, the other muſtindure for euer, accordynge to this ſayinge of chriſte. Heauen and earth ſhall peryſhe but my worde ſhall endure for euer. But nowe my chapleyus percepuynge that they can nod longer mayntayne me with ſtoute and ſteborne wordes. They begyn to be aſhamed of my na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me &amp; call me a ſacrifyſe, which ought to be offred vp for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people, alas good foles, do you yet thynbe to blynde men as ye haue done. No no it is perceaued well ynough y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chriſt offred hym ones for al. And you ſhal not nede to be aſha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med of me for I wyll departe vnto my father the Pope from whenſe I came. Wherfore I gyue you warnyng euery one to prouyde for hymſelfe aſwell as he can, you maye reade that S. Paule wroughte for his lyuyng and yet prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed the wordeſyncerely, and gaue all
<pb facs="tcp:6700:7"/>men warnynge to be the folowers of hym as he was the folower of Chriſte, be not you aſhamed therfore to worke for your lyuyng whiche cannot preach nor wyll take no paynes therin. And tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke your owne pryde and ſlou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes therof for I aſure you there is very fewe whiche wyll be ſory for your myſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunce.</p>
            <p>But yet by my trueth it greueth me for olde aquaintans to here my<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>haplayns go vp &amp; downe wepyng, and waylynge and bytterly lamentyng this my depar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tynge. Alas laye they all wyll to the dyuell, oure confeſſion is almoſt gone, and our maſſe wyl away, it was neuer other lyke ſens it was laufull for euery Iacke ſcrapſcall to rede the Byble and teſtamente. Then we myghte beſure that all wolde to nought and that oure crafte wol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e be perceyued. Au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ngence of them allſaye they for nowe we that can not preach, muſt he fayne to worke for our lyuyng, alas ſyr ſarth one wyll
<pb facs="tcp:6700:7"/>it not be a ſtraunge ſyght to ſe a prieſt handell a ſpade, mat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke, ſhouyll, dung forke, or any ſuch vyle thynges: which was wont to handell a gylten chalys a fayre maſſe booke a payre of ſyluer ſences and ſuch pratye thynges. Well I can not remedy it: Ther is no faulte that they can layein me for I gaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> warnynge longe ago and tolde them that I muſt begone. Wherfore nowe I take my leaue at you all. Fare well gentyll audyence: and I pray you bere me wytnee that I haue here erneſtlye reucket &amp; vtterly denyed all my powre and aucthoryte. Confeſſynge that it was but a falſe iuencion of my father, and his ſucceſſors for lukets ſake Fare well my chaplaynes all. I pray you let me not eſcape out of your memorye. Fare well olde frende fryday, and haue me commendyd vnto your brother ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terdaye. Fare well gentyll Iacke of lent, for I thynke you be not readye to go with me. Adue good ymber dayes
<pb facs="tcp:6700:8"/>and commende me to youre coſyn <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>dans daye for I thinke I ſhall ouer take our frende <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>gation dayes. Fare well golden copes &amp; go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gious veſteme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, for Iean carye none of you with me, bycauſe I go on fote, commends me I pray you, to my truſty ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes the exeſſe, the cruer, the ſantus bell, the great belles in the ſtepyll w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theyr ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes, alſo haue me co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſſe b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke the manuell, with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> proceſioners Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mende me alſo to my truſty ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, the chales the corprace, whiche ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer dyſceaued me. And haue me co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended to all the reſt as well as thoughe I reher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them by name.</p>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>¶ The .i. day of June</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>by me maiſtres Miſſa the oldeſt doughter vnto the Pope</signed>
            </closer>
            <closer>God ſaue the Kynge.</closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:6700:8"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
